Lafayette mss., 1572-1939 LMC 2326
Lilly Library
- Manuscripts
  - Chronological
    - William King to Brigadier Geul Payson - Regarding differences with other officers over the treatment of deserters, 1814, October 10; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 17)
      "William King (?-1826) commanded in the Black Rock Canadian Expedition of 1812, in which he was wounded and taken prisoner. He was a Major at the capture of York (now Toronto) and later wounded at Fort George, May 1813."
    - James Wilkinson (General) to Col. Van Rensselaer, 1814, November 3; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Charles Dambray to Monsieur le Premier President, 1815, February 28; ADS (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Lafayette to Madison - Speaking of the late war between Great Britain and the United States, he states that he would have volunteered on the American side, 1815, March 26; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Alexandre, Comte de Lameth, to Lamardelle, 1815, March 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      "Alexandre, Count de Lameth (1760-1829) was an Aide under Rochambeau in the American Revolution. He writes from Amiens thanking Lamardelle for the courtesies extended to M. Amye, an old hussar, whose pension is in question, apparently because of the fall of the Empire, and asking for the continuance of Lamardelle's interest in the matter."
    - Lafayette to Lanjuinais - President of the Chamber - "I hope that you have received the acceptance of the Emperor", 1815, June 5; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Rousselin (St. Albin) - Concerning Mondollot, one of his bodyguards on Oct. 6, 1789, 1815, June 6; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Rousselin (St. Albin) - About M. Voisin and the matter of the "Cross" for M. Mondollot, 1815, June 14; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Marie-Therese (of Austria), Queen of Sardinia to Louis Philippe - She tells her cousin of the reestablishment of her uncle on the Throne of Naples. Commiserates with Louis and his family on their exile, 1815, July 7; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      "Maria Theresa Jeanne Josephine of Austria (1773-1832), Queen of Sardinia to Louis Philippe, later King of the French after the Revolution of 1830"
    - Duc d'Alberg to a Prince (?) - "We must congratulate ourselves on the quick ending....I have just read the proclamation signed by you and I regard its statements as admirable", 1815, July 11; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Includes translated extracts
    - Lafayette to Girout Pouzol - Discussing the questions of the day with "Mon cher Ancien Collegue", 1815, July 21; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Mr. Crawford, Secretary of War - I have declined the peerage - the abdication of the Emperor and the removal of his person and his family from the Capital - instead of a Council of Regency, a provisory government of five elected members. Napoleon had his choice of exile in America, 1815, August 4; Photostat 6 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Also includes clippings about letter, which reveals that Napoleon turned down U.S. citizenship in favor of exile
    - Tobias Lear - Official paper, 1815, August 25; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Country boy, Jonathan, visits the "big city" of Albany, N.Y. and writes home of the customs and fashions of the day, 1815, August; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to unknown - Introducing M. de Vendel, who is coming to America after being "cleared of an accusation of correspondence with the Isle of Elbe", 1815, October 8; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Monroe - Reflecting the swiftly changing political conditions in France, he writes - "I have before me your kind letter of April 24, under the reign you thought, of Louis XVIII, while Napoleon had been for a month seated again on his Imperial Throne. Now that I answer, the Bonapartian reign has long been at an end and the Royal family are restored to the government of France", 1815, November 2; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Louis Guerin, baron de Bruslart, to ?, 1815, November 10; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
      "Louis Guerin, Baron de Bruslart, served in the American Revolution."
    - Antonio Canova to "Signore", 1815, December 4; ADS (Box 3, Folder 18)
      "Antonio Canova was born in 1757 in the village of Possagno, studied in Venice and Rome. His "Theseus" executed in 1782 was thought to vie with classic art and he was regarded as the founder of a new school. After he had completed his "Clement XIV" (1787) he did many beautiful works with a grace peculiar to him. His famous "Pius VI" has a unique position in St. Peter's at Rome. Canova was Curator of Art under Pius VII. In 1815 he was sent to Paris to reclaim the art works that had been taken out of Italy by Napoleon, and while there he visited England."
    - Lafayette to unknown - "My family, increased by the birth of a boy, George's son, are with me", 1815, December 13; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Sir John Coghill - News about their American friends Mr. Parker and Mrs. Baldwin - "I am fixed for the winter in a rural retreat in which you have seen me, under the 'Napoleoncan' Government, during many years, a constant inhabitant", 1815, December 13; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to General Ross - It would have been a most pleasing gratification to renew their old acquaintance and talk of old times, 1815, December 23; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "First Act of Incorporation in the world for a Steam Railroad passed by a Legislative or Pariliamentary Body" by Col. Stevens, 1815; Typed document 8 p. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lafayette to Skipwith, 1816, January 20; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette to Madison (?) - A long letter on European politics, 1816, January 25; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette to Monroe - A new Minister to the United States has been elected - writes of du Plansier, Bushrod Washington, Mr. Gallatin, Mr. Clay, 1816, February 15; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette to Madison - "Adieu, my dear sir, the glory, prosperity, liberty and happiness of the U.S., the justice done to their Government, are to me sources of enjoyment never more necessary than in the present European times - although there is nobody in France more confident of future European freedom and less despairing of our situation", 1816, February 16; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Petition by Sir William Antoine (?) de Moly to the effect that he should be made President of the Court of first instance at Montaubon (?), in view of the fact that he has lost, by its abolition, the position of a member of the King's Court at Toulouse, and sets forth in support of his application, his political conduct since the Restoration. He is not satisfied with his present position as substitute, for which he had not asked. Under date of Marh 30, 1816, Louis Antoine de Bourbon, recommends with interest, the applicant as capable of filling the position. The paper does not indicate the result of the recommendation.", 1816, March 30; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Louis Antoine de Bourbon, Duc d'Angouleme (1775-1844), left France with his father (Charles X) after the Revolution. IN 1799 he married Marie Therese, only daughter of Louis XVI. Angouleme made a feeble attempt to oppose Napoleon on his return from Elba. In the Revolution of 1830 he accompanied his father into exile."
    - Power of Attorney appointing Elbridge Gerry for Ann Gerry's estate - Taken by James T. Austin, who married one of the Gerry daughters, and who wrote "a Life of Elbridge Gerry", 1816, May 1; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Ann Gerry, wife of Elbridge Gerry - She was the daughter of Charles Thomson, Secretary of the Continental Congress."
    - Edmund Charles Genet, envoy to United States during the French Revolution, to Spencer Stafford - Regarding a demand for wheat, 1816, May 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Francois Antoine, Comte Boissy d'Anglas, to de Vigny, a senior inspector of surveys - Regarding some aspects of the settlement of an estate, 1816, June 10; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Francois Antoine, Comte Boissy d'Anglas (1756-1826) - secretary of the Convention, member of the Committee of Public Safety - assisted in the overthrow of Robespierre - President of the Council of Five Hundred."
    - Jean F. Hilaire to Monsieur Normand, premier des finances, 1816, June 20; ADS (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Jean F. Hilaire, French Revolutionist, Prefect of Haute Saone, 1724-1825"
    - Stephen Longfellow to John T. Apthorp, 1816, July 24; ADS (Box 3, Folder 19)
      "Stephen Longfellow (1775-1849) was born in Maine and practised law in Portland. He was a delegate to the Hartford Convention of 1814, and later served in Congress as a Federalist, and was a member of the House at the time of Lafayette's visit in 1825. He married the daughter of General Peleg Wadsworth, an Officer in the Revolution. Their son Henry Wadsworth Longfellow was born in 1807 and became one of America's great poets."
    - Lafayette - Mentions Monroe, Clay, Madison, W. H. Crawford, Gallatin, Joel Parker and Jonathan Meigs, 1816, July 28; ADS (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette to Madison - Current questions of the day, 1816, August 18; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Thomas B. Adams to James Sproat, 1816, October 3; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette - Recommending de Mange, the younger - "His father served me for a long time and who was for several months my companion in captivity", 1816, October 22; ADS (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette to Comte de Suffren - On negotiations which Madame de Lusignem, his aunt will conduct, 1816, December 14; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Lafayette about de Suffren to ?, 1816, December 26; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Paul-Jacques de Bruyères-Chalabre - Certificate, 1816, December 30; ADS (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Governor Joseph Bloomfield to Garret Dorset Wall - Explaining a "Nun", 1817, January 7; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      "The addressee, Garret Dorset Wall, was born in New Jersey 1783, educated for the law, commanded a volunteer company from Trenton in 1812, held various public offices and in 1835 was elected Governor of New Jersey. But declined that he might accept the United States senatorship, where he served until 1841. He became a member of the New Jersey Court of Errors and Appeals in 1849, in which he sat until his death in 1850."
    - Charles Dambray to M. du Chilleau, 1817, February 7; ADS (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Lafayette to Lady Morgan - He replies to her request for his comment on "certain details about the last political moments of Napoleon", 1817, February 10; Photostat 5 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Also includes summary of contents and typed translation into English
    - Lafayette to Sir John Coghill, 1817, February 16; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Louis de Ghaisnes, Comte de Bourmont, to Monsieur de Fresne, 1817, February 27; ADS (Box 3, Folder 20)
      "Louis de Ghaisnes, Comte de Bourmont (1773-1846), went into exile during the Revolution but returned to fight in La Vendee. He attached himself to Napoleon and for his brilliant services was made a General in 1813. He declared for the Bourbons in 1814, but joined Napoleon on the return from Elba, only to desert him again on the eve of Ligny. His evidence went far to bring about Ney's execution. In 1830 he was made a Marshal of France."
    - Lafayette to Tripier - Concerning his mother's estate, 1817, March 22; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Lafayette recommends that the "Badge of the Cincinnati" be conferred on a fellow Frenchman who had fought in the American Revolution - Probably addressed to President Madison, 1817, March 30; ADS 2 p. (copy) (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Includes photostat of original
    - Robert Vicomte Castlereagh, 1817, April 15 (Ovflat 30)
    - David Hosack to John Lanshan (?), 1817, April 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      David Hosack, 1769-1835 - scientist, physician, teacher, historian"
    - William Wolcott Ellsworth to Ebenezer Lane, 1817, May 7; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 20)
      "William Wolcott Ellsworth (1791-1868), a son of Oliver Ellsworth, was a lawyer, and a member of Congress from Connecticut. He prepared the present Copyright Law of the United States, after exhaustive search and study. He was Governor of Connecticut in 1838, serving three terms."
    - Lafayette to M. Tripier - His son is going to Paris and will present himself, 1817, May 27; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Appointment of Samuel Grosvenor as Judge - Signed by Oliver Wolcott, Governor of Connecticut, 1817, May 30; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Duke of Kent, father of Queen Victoria - Acknowledging Doctor Hankin's favor, 1817, June 26; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Richard Bland Lee to Madison, 1817, July 2; ADS (Box 3, Folder 21)
      "After the close of his second term as President, in 1817, Mr. Madison retired to his estate at Montpelier, where he spent nearly twenty happy yeras with books and friends. Richard Bland Lee writes the above letter of felicitations and good wishes."
    - Receipt of payment - Henry Clinton, 1817, August 26; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 21)
      "Sir Henry Clinton, 1771-1829, was General Henry Clinton's second son. He also became a General and was one of Wellington's favorite Officers."
    - Lafayette to Comte de Mun - Speaks of Mr. Ticknor, his American visitor, 1817, September; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      "NOTE - George Ticknor (1791-1871), the author, spent the years 1815 to 1819 visiting and studying literature, in Europe."
    - Lafayette to Peyre, 1817, October 7; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lafayette to Madame Jullien - Desires the return of the English work entitled "History of the Boroughs of Great Britain" - would like to hear about her family, 1817, October 9; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Charles Carroll of Carrollton - Authorizing James Sterrett to sign in his name, 1817, October 10; ADS (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Major General Jacob Brown to President Monroe - A private letter telling of his roundabout trip home, evidently the same route which Monroe had recently taken - the people are friendly to the Administration - Governor Clinton of New York desires amicable relations between his State and the National Government, 1817, November 2 (Ovflat 30)
    - Lafayette to Sir Charles Morgan - Discussing literature and politics - "Europe seems to have given herself governments not to protect but to hinder the exchange of ideas, of sentiments, and of material enjoyment", 1817, November 9; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lafayette to Tripier - On his affairs with de Suffren - refers to Moritor "who had charge of my business up to the time he stated his accounts with the Government in January 1813", 1817, November 13; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lafayette to Tripier - Mentions Victor Latour Maubourg, de Suffren and Charles Maubourg, 1817, December 6; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lafayette to Bertemy - Apparently Bertemy was his Agent in making a loan to Tremoilles. Lafayette thinks he should have interest, but is willing to make concessions in view of the hard times, 1817, December 20; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Jonathan Mason to Jeffry Richardson, 1818, January 29; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      "Eyewitness to Boston Massacre - Jonathan Mason (1752-1831) as a boy of eighteen years was an onlooker when the British troops fired on a small group of people in the streets of Boston. On the tenth anniversary of the Massacre, in 1780, he delivered the official oration before the authorities of Boston. Mason was many times a member of his State Legislature, and in 1800 Massachusetts sent him to the United States Senate. He retired in 1803, but was again sent to Washington as a Federalist Congressman in 1817. Mason was a skillful lawyer and a ready debater."
    - Lafayette to Lady Morgan on literature and politics - He tells her the story of a Scotch soldier who, after the capitulation at Yorktown, said to a French Grenadier - "You fight for your King and I fight for mine - that is very simple, but the Americans, for whom do they fight?", 1818, February 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Copy of a bond by John Stevens, 1818, March 30; Typed document 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Tripier, 1818, April 15; Photostat (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Princess Elizabeth, daughter of George III - Receipt of the Queen's engraving commands, 1818, May 15; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - William H. Crawford to William Jones, President of the Bank of the United States, 1818, April 23; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - New Hampshire, 1818, June 10 (Ovflat 30)
    - John Stevens, Sr. to Alexander I, Emperor of Russia - Referring to a proposal that he had made to Mr. Daschkoff, the Russian Minister to U.S., that Stevens could and would build Steam Frigates for the Russians, ships far superior to sailing vessels, as they could be propelled at the rate of at least seven miles per hour and could navigate the roughest seas, 1818, June 18; Typed document 12 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      "NOTE - Attached to the letter (which refers to it) there is a detailed Report of Lt. Col. James House to Governor D. D. Tompkins of New York, on an invention by John Stevens, Jr. for the making of elongated shells. Stevens had agreed to make them for no other Government that the United States if an appropriation was forthcoming, but that three years had elapsed and as there was no present possibility of war between the United States and any other power, Stevens would entertain a contract to supply shells for the Russians."
    - Ship license for Macculloch Clansie - Signed by George III, 1818, July 4; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Lafitte - "I am no longer in the plight of being affected by the law and our bargain could not have been better from my point of view", 1818, July 21; Photostat 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Sir Charles Morgan - HE compares the election systems in England, France and America, 1818, August 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Sir Charles Morgan - Is happy that he will visit them. He and Lady Morgan will be very welcome. Among his present guests is the "distinguished young painter Ary Scheffer", 1818, September 3; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
      "NOTE - Scheffer's portrait of Lafayette hangs in the Chamber of the House of Representatives, Washington, D. C."
    - Lafayette to Jullien - His view is that the Government will beat down all oposition to the "Holy Alliance", 1818, September 22; Photostat 3 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Col. Stevens to President James Monroe - He proposes to build a steam railroad from the Delaware River, near Trenton, to the Raritan River, near New Brunswick and believes that the United States Government should assist in this as a part of its plan for "internal improvement", 1818, October 21; Typed document 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Charolois - Thanks him for the evidence of friendship shown him on his entry into the Chamber of Deputies. In the postscript he refers to his colleagues of 1815, 1818, November 11; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to de la Bergerie - "My correspondence with General Washington was destroyed during my proscription. I have left, however, some letters of mine and very few of his which were sent me from the United States", 1818, November 16; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Includes handwritten translation into English
    - Lafayette to Sir Charles Morgan - Rumors of Napoleon's attempt at escape, 1818, November 18; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Lady Morgan - Compliments her on her new book - "Florence Macarthy", 1818, November 23; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - William Ellery at Collectors Office, Port of Newport - Regarding the case of the Schooner San Roman, 1818, November 25; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to his fellow Deputy, de la Haie. He is coming up for the Session and wants to discuss matters, 1818, December 1; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette to Sir Charles Morgan - Giving an intimation of Lafayette's wide field of current reading, 1818, December 2; ADS (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Lafayette household account book - prepared by T. M. Pontonnier, consists of forty leaves and is bound in modern red morroco; bears the approval signatures of General Lafayette and his son George Washington Lafayette with later appended dates of 1819, Jan. 1; May 18; and 1824, Jan. 30. The signature of W. P. Gardner on a fly leaf indicates the volume was formerly a part of the Gardner collection, 1814-1818 (Bound 1)
    - Lafayette to Lady Morgan - Social note, 1819, February; ADS (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Prince de Hesse-Darmstadi, 1819, March 20 (Ovflat 30)
    - Chambre des Deputes Assemblee, 1819, April 30 (Ovflat 30)
    - Massachusetts - Alden Bradford, 1819, May 4 (Ovflat 30)
    - Charles Dambray to Monsieur de la Barre, 1819, May 12; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Etienne Macdonald, Duc de Tarente, to M. le Comte Pelet de la Lozere, 1819, May 29; Printed document with autograph fill-ins, signed (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Lafayette to M. de l'Albin - On the reassembling of the Chambers. "I have sought with much interest in "the Constitutional" for the announcement of the work of Vicomte de Ledon", 1819, October 22; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Marechal de Viomenil to ?, 1819, November 3; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Lafayette to St. Albin - On current politics, 1819, November 8; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - George W. Lafayette to ? - Mentions Joseph Greenier, the makeup of the Chambre, de Broglie, and Madame Girot (Possibly this letter is to her husband), 1819, December 21; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Le Marshal Viomenil to ?, 1819, December 28; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 23)
      "Charles Joseph Hyacinthe du Houx, Marquis de Viomenil (1734-1827), was aide-de-camp to General Chevert at the taking of Prague in 1757, commanded at Corsica 1768, and reached the grade of Major General in 1780. He came to America under his brother, the Baron, who was second in command to Rochambeau. He was Commander of the French Artillery at Yorktown. At the time of the French Revolution he became an emigre in 1791, served in the Army of Conde 1792-1797, and was Commander-in-Chief of the Portuguese Army 1800-1808. After the restoration, Louis XVIII made him a Peer of France, and he became a Marquis in 1817."
    - Lafayette to President James Monroe - In that "Aristocracy of the Land there is a great majority averse to the Ancien Regime and attached to National Honor", 1820, January 15; Photostat 4 p. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Receipt - Prince Charles de Broglie, Louis Philippe's Prime Minister, 1820, February 3; ADS (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - William Wirt to Timoathy Fuller, 1820, February 24; ADS (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - New Hampshire - Levi Jones, 1820, March 2 (Ovflat 30)
    - Robert Troup to Stephen von Renssalaer, 1820, March 4; ADS 2 p. (Box 3, Folder 24)
      "NOTE - This is the signature of Robert, not Richard Troup - the letter was written by him at the age of 84."
    - Louis, 1820, March 11 (Ovflat 30)
    - Francis Scott Key - Authorizing Henry M. Murray to transfer stock for him, 1820, May 3; ADS on scrapbook page (Box 3, Folder 24)
      "Author of 'Star Spangled Banner' - Francis Scott Key (1780-1843) was the son of a soldier of the Revolution. During the British attack on Baltimore in the War of 1812, Key was in a position to observe the flag at Fort McHenry, and on the morning after, when he saw the flag still flying, his feelings found expression in the verses of what has become our National Anthem."